In the near future, the world
stands on the brink of destruction.
3 young pilots mature as
they operate gigantic machines
against the attacks of mysterious alien beings.
Today we have director of the hit anime Neon
Genesis Evangelion, Anno Hideaki.
Anno, you've hit it big.
Me? Big?
What do you mean?
It doesn't feel like I've hit it big.
Ok, so I watched Eva from start to
finish and thought it was amazing,
but all of these anime communities
are highlighting you like,
"Anno Hideaki, up and coming
with the younger generation."
It doesn't strike me that way.
Really?
But, haven't people been
paying more attention to you?
Are people paying more attention?
Seriously, nothing like that sticks out to me.
When would you say you first started
developing an interest in movies?
When I was a kid I was more
into TV shows than movies.
I was raised on TV.
Was that mainly anime and tokusatsu?
Yeah, and other dramas like that.
Aside from that, I was raised normally.
I looked up to tokusatsu and the hero genre,
but I never thought about making it.
Making heroes?
Around high school, I started
getting into film. Like the 8mm.
Live filming?
Yeah, yeah. 8mm.
I worked on both anime and live film.
Out of the blue?
Out of the blue.
Was there someone who inspired you to start?
I wanted to try my hand at it.
I was hit with this sudden desire and went with it.
After messing around for a bit the quality
just started heading in its own direction.
I guess.
When you first started, did you practice
drawing movement with flip-books?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
When you first started, did you practice
drawing movement with flip-books?
Before high school, I didn't have a textbook I could
work in, so I wasn't aware of what I could do.
I wanted to draw, but they have those annoying pictures
that show up along the edges where
you aren't supposed to write, right?
Right.
My high school textbooks didn't have those.
So it was easy to draw flip-book art.
Exactly.
[Poor Gunner]
Early Works
Was Poor Gunner your first animated piece?
Actually, I did draw something
before that during high school,
but I have no idea where that went.
Poor Gunner, was made during your time off school?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
During that time, hmmm what was
it? I felt I needed to hone my skills.
You were doing what you like.
It was training.
Training is boring.
Not all of it, but more likely than not, it's boring.
When I first watched Poor Gunner,
it felt so nostalgic like I'd seen
something similar to it before.
I mean, there was something like it.
What did you draw that on?
Daiei scratch paper.
Scratch paper, like for calculations?
Daiei, like the company?
Yeah. yeah.
On scratch paper?
Yep.
And you drew it page by page?
Yeah, yeah.
I didn't have the technical knowledge to
know about time sheets and stuff like that.
I just drew what felt right
and worked on it part-time.
I worked with a group where we would start
individually and then bring everything together.
I think... I think that was then that
your ANNO signature first appeared.
Yes, yes, yes.
That signature hasn't changed since then, has it?
It hasn't. It hasn't changed since middle school.
A-N-N
-O
In art club, during middle school,
we naturally created our own art.
We wanted to distinguish ourselves
by adding signatures to the corner.
For oil paintings.
It's the same signature from back then.
[Tough Tire! SHADO Tire]
Freshman year of college
Um, wait, "Hataraku Kuruma" is the name of that
children's car song; what was your car animation?
Tough Tire?
Tough Tire! I was off by a long shot! Sorry!
Very long.
The car moved so precisely.
It bounced and drove around so well,
I thought "what are SHADO tires?"
and ended up watching again and again.
The motions were so fluid it felt like I
was watching an overseas cartoon.
Oh that's because I animated on ones,
so it was bound to come out fluid.
Does animating on ones tend to be more fluid?
Much more fluid.
Why?
Film has 24 frames per second.
Animating on ones means there is a
different drawing each of the 24 frame.
With most anime, out of the 24 frames,
only 8 frames are shown per second.
24 divided by 8 means it's animated on threes.
It's like that because of how you animated it?
Yeah, it appears to be moving about 3
times faster than standard TV anime.
Well, it sounds weird to
say it's moving 3 times faster.
Wasn't that a rather high-quality
animation for a college student's work?
It appears that way. I don't recall much about it.
Did it get any praise?
It was formally recognized.
Did you make it by yourself?
All by myself.
No way.
I think, wow, there was a time
Anno put out these kinds of shorts.
These kinds of shorts, huh.
Yeah, it took me by surprise.
Huh, from how I see it, it's nothing all
that unusual in the animation world.
Director Anno didn't just work on anime
but also worked with his fellow students
to create tokusatsu in pursuit of the
heroes he looked up to as a child.
One of those projects was Patriotic Squadron Great Japan.
Love!
Could we move away from
anime and into tokusatsu?
Yes.
You worked on Patriotic Squadron Great Japan.
It reminded me of Battle Fever J.
They're both sentai squads after all.
For that, for that you...
I assisted on set.
Assisted? As the what?
The mechanical designer?
As the designer, but also as the optical
effects person - the animation like effects.
I also wore the suits.
You did? Which color character?
Oh, no, I was in the robot or monster suits.
You did the narrations as well?
Yes, I narrated some parts.
Jinpu Takeshi trains around the
clock, ready for any emergency.
Their fight is only just beginning.
This was only the first step
toward protecting their country.
Your narration has a distinctive presence to it.
That, that was just me talking.
It was sufficient.
What material did you use for all the
transforming and combining robots?
Paper.
Paper?
So you put the paper...wait, no,
how did you connect it all together?
Industrial strength glue.
It's paper crafting.